Guide to the David Hamburg papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
David Hamburg papers
1949-2003.
Hamburg, David A., 1925-
353 linear ft. (836 document boxes, 5 flat boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
CA#0005
5419526
David A. Hamburg Papers (1950 - 2004, 841 boxes) document life and work of David A. Hamburg, a scholar, public health expert and president of Carnegie Corporation of New York from 1982 to 1997, who helped improve the quality of life and education for young people and worked to prevent violent conflict among nations
History
Born in 1925 in Evansville, Indiana, David Alan Hamburg attended Indiana University and its medical school, receiving his M.D. in 1947. In the 1950s, Hamburg, a psychiatrist, distinguished himself as a pioneering investigator of stress and anxiety beginning at the Walter Reed Army Institute of Research, Washington, D.C. (1952-53) and then at the Institute for Psychosomatic and Psychiatric Research and Training at the Michael Reese Hospital, Chicago (1953-56). Hamburg continued his research at the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Stanford, CA. As chair of psychiatry at Stanford University School of Medicine, Hamburg established a new department of psychiatry and behavioral sciences, distinguished by its breadth of research on behavioral biology, especially in relation to mental illness. While chief of the adult psychiatry branch at the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH, 1958-61), he created one of the nation's first clinical research centers to combine psychological and biological factors in studying depression.
In 1975, while serving as Reed-Hodgson Professor of Human Biology at Stanford (1972-76), Hamburg was confronted with a crisis that would re-direct his focus from psychiatric research to contemporary social problems. Four of Hamburg’s students, studying primate behavior under the direction of Jane Goodall at a remote research station in Gombe, Tanzania, were abducted by armed rebels from Zaire (now Congo) and held for ransom and other demands. Hamburg immediately flew to Gombe and spent 10 weeks negotiating their release.
His vivid exposure to violence, disease and poverty during this time prompted him to devote his energies to using science to help meet social needs. In 1975 he became president of the Institute of Medicine, the health policy arm of the National Academy of Sciences, where he developed major initiatives on health and behavior, health promotion and disease prevention, and the health needs of the underserved as well as developing nations. From 1980 to 1983, Hamburg served as director of the university-wide Division of Health Policy Research and Education and John D. MacArthur Professor of Health Policy at Harvard University, Cambridge, MA., applying his signature cross-disciplinary approach to health policy issues.
After David Hamburg became president of Carnegie Corporation of New York in December 1982, the Corporation sought to mobilize the best scientific and scholarly talent and thinking to address contemporary issues from early childhood to international relations, using a comprehensive inter-disciplinary approach.
During Hamburg’s tenure as president, the Corporation placed a priority on the education and healthy development of children and adolescents and the preparation of youth for a scientific, technological and knowledge-driven world. Three major study groups were formed to cover the educational and developmental needs of children and youth from birth to age 15: the Carnegie Council on Adolescent Development (1986), the Carnegie Task Force on Meeting the Needs of Young Children (1991), and the Carnegie Task Force on Learning in the Primary Grades (1994). Jointly with the Rockefeller Foundation, Carnegie Corporation also financed the National Commission on Teaching and America's Future, whose report, What Matters Most (1996), provided a framework and agenda for teacher education reform across the country. Characteristically these study groups drew on the knowledge generated by the previous Carnegie grant programs and from relevant fields and inspired follow up grantmaking to implement the recommendations. At that time David Hamburg also chaired the Forum on Adolescence, a joint effort of the Institute of Medicine and National Research Council to assess adolescent health and development.
In 1984, the Corporation established the Carnegie Commission on Education and the Economy. Through its major publication, A Nation Prepared (1986), the foundation reaffirmed the role of the teacher as the "best hope" for ensuring educational excellence in elementary and secondary education. An outgrowth of that report was the establishment, a year later, of the National Board for Professional Teaching Standards to consider ways of attracting able candidates to the teaching profession and recognizing and retaining them. At the Corporation's initiative, the American Association for the Advancement of Science issued two groundbreaking reports, Science for All Americans (1989) and Benchmarks for Science Literacy (1993), which recommended a common core of learning in science, mathematics, and technology for all citizens and helped set national standards of achievement in these domains.
Hamburg introduced an entirely new focus for the Corporation --- the danger to world peace posed by the superpower confrontation and weapons of mass destruction. The foundation underwrote scientific study of the feasibility of the proposed federal Strategic Defense Initiative and joined the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation in supporting the analytic work of a new generation of arms control and nuclear nonproliferation experts. After the collapse of the Soviet Union, Corporation grants helped promote the concept of cooperative security among erstwhile adversaries and projects to build democratic institutions in the former Soviet Union and central Europe. An important undertaking was the Prevention of Proliferation Task Force, coordinated under a grant to the Brookings Institution, which inspired the Nunn–Lugar Amendment to the Soviet Threat Reduction Act of 1991 aimed at dismantling Soviet nuclear weapons and reducing proliferation risks. Beginning in the mid-1990s, the Corporation addressed the problems of interethnic and regional conflict and supported projects seeking to diminish the risks of a wider war stemming from civil strife. Two Carnegie commissions, one on Reducing the Nuclear Danger (1990), the other on Preventing Deadly Conflict (1994), together addressed the full range of dangers associated with human conflict and the use of weapons of mass destruction. The Corporation's thrust in Commonwealth Africa, meanwhile, shifted to women’s health and leadership development and the application of science and technology, including new information systems, in fostering research and expertise within indigenous scientific institutions and universities.
Under Hamburg, dissemination achieved even greater primacy in the arsenal of strategic philanthropy. Emphasis was on consolidation and diffusion of the best available knowledge from social science and education research and the use of such research in improving social policy and practice. Major partners in these endeavors were leading institutions that had the capability to influence public thought and action. Hamburg made increasing use of the Corporation’s powers to convene leaders and experts across disciplinary and sectoral boundaries to forge policy consensus and promote collaboration.
In the international security field, Hamburg served on many policy advisory boards, including the Executive Panel for the Chief of Naval Operations, the National Academy of Sciences Committee on International Security and Arms Control, and the U.S.-Soviet Joint Study Group on Crisis Prevention. He was a member of the Defense Policy Board of the Department of Defense and co-chair, with Cyrus Vance, of the Carnegie Commission on Preventing Deadly Conflict. In 2006, Hamburg was appointed by United Nations Secretary-General Kofi Annan to chair the UN Advisory Committee on Genocide Prevention.
In science policy, he chaired several national groups, including committees and advisory boards of the Institute of Medicine, National Institute of Mental Health, and the National Science Foundation. From 1976 to 1988, he served on the Advisory Committee on Medical Research of the World Health Organization. He was president and board chair of the American Association for the Advancement of Science from 1984 to 1986. The Carnegie Commission on Science, Technology, and Government (1988-1993), recommended ways that government at all levels could make more effective use of science and technology in their operations and policies. In 1994, Hamburg was appointed to the President's Committee of Advisors on Science and Technology, and in 1996, he was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom, the nation’s highest civilian honor.
From his background in public health, he brought a preventive orientation to serious problems. Across all of these programs, the common thread, said Hamburg, is the "prevention of rotten outcomes." Hamburg believed that "from child and adolescent development to international relations, the underlying logic is the same: Prevention begins with anticipation, even with long-range foresight, in which research can identify risk factors and point to steps that can be taken to counteract or avoid an undesirable outcome, and pivotal institutions can cooperate in shaping behavior away from risk factors and dangerous directions."
Hamburg served on the boards of Rockefeller University, the Mount Sinai Medical Center, and the American Museum of Natural History, New York City; and the Johann Jacobs Foundation, Zurich. He was a member of the American Philosophical Society and the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, as well as author of numerous books and scholarly articles.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of correspondence, memoranda, documents, minutes, reports, manuscripts, notes, calendars, photographs, audio recordings, awards and other realia and printed materials. The correspondence and memoranda are of various scientists and educators, public figures, leaders of organized philanthropy, government officials, board members and staff of various national, foreign and international organizations It relates to clinical and field research, policy development, administrative responsibilities, teaching, writing and speaking, performed by Dr. David Hamburg throughout his long and distinguished career.
Arrangement
Arranged in 14 series:
Series I. Carnegie Corporation of New York, 1965-2003
Subseries I.1. Board Meetings, 1985-1997
Subseries I.2. Trustee files, 1983-2000
Subseries I.3. Strengthening Human Resources in Developing Countries, 1982-1997
Subseries I.4. South Africa, 1983-1996
Subseries I.5. Carnegie Commission for Science, Technology and Development, 1977-1992
Subseries I.6. Children & Youth, 1983-2001
Subseries I.7. Preventing Deadly Conflict, 1965-2003
Sub-Subseries I.7.A Chronological Files, 1983-2003
Sub-Subseries I.7.B. Background Materials, 1972-2003
Sub-Subseries I.7.C. “Stages” Files, 1983-1993
Sub-Subseries I.7.D. Alphabetical Subject Files, 1965-1997
Subseries I.8. Eastern Block and Avoiding Nuclear War, 1965-2002
Sub-Subseries I.8.A Chronological Files, 1982 – 2002
Sub-Subseries I.8.B. Background Materials, 1965-2002
Sub-Subseries I.8.C. Velikhov Project, 1985-1992
Subseries I.9. General and Administrative, 1979-1998
Subseries I.10. Committee on International Security and Arms Control (CISAC), 1982-1987
Series II. U.S. Government Work, 1984-2001
Subseries II.1. President's Committee of Advisors on Science and Technology Policy (PCAST), 1993 – 2001
Subseries II.2. Presidential Advisory Committee on Gulf War Veterans Illnesses, 1995-1998
Subseries II.3. Office of President Clinton, 1992-1999
Subseries II.4: Secretary of Energy Advisory Board, 1990-1994
Subseries II.5 Chief of Naval Operations Executive Panel, 1984-1997
Series III. Correspondence, 1957-2003
Subseries III.1. Individuals, 1957-2003
Subseries III.2. Institutions, 1971-2003
Subseries III.3. Chronological, 1987-2001
Series IV. Stanford University, 1944-2003
Series V. Institute of Medicine, 1952-1997
Series VI. Harvard University, 1975-2003
Series VII. Other Board and Advisory Work, 1974-2002
Subseries VII.1 American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1981-2000
Subseries VII.2 American Museum of Natural History, 1985-2000
Subseries VII.3: The Carter Center, 1988-2002
Subseries VII.4: The Jacobs Foundation 1988-1998
Subseries VII.5: Mt. Sinai Medical Center 1980-2001
Subseries VII.6 National Academy of Sciences, 1995-2001
Subseries VII.7: National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH), 1974 - 1986
Subseries VII.8: Pocantico Institute of Technology, 1986-1989
Subseries VII.9: Rockefeller University, 1984-2001
Series VIII. Early Career, 1941-1966
Series IX. United Nations Agencies, 1971-2003
Series X. Writings and Speeches, 1949-2003
Subseries X.1: Educating for Conflict Resolution, 1974-2003
Subseries X.2. Children and Youth, 1980-1994
Subseries X.3: General, 1949-2003
Series XI. Biographical Materials, 1949-2003
Subseries XI:1 Personal, 1949-1999
Subseries XI.2: Emeritus, 1999-2003
Series XII. Background Research Materials, 1950-2000
Series XIII. Audiovisual, 1974-2000
Series XIV. Realia,1970-2001
Subjects
Carnegie Commission on Preventing Deadly Conflict.; Carnegie Council on Children.; Carnegie Commission on Science, Technology, and Government.; Carnegie Council on Adolescent Development.; Harvard University. Division of Health Policy Research and Education.; National Academies (U.S.). National Academy of Sciences.; Institute of Medicine (U.S.); Stanford University.; United Nations.; Hamburg, David A., 1925-; Gregorian, Vartan.; Clinton, Bill, 1946-.; Clinton, Hillary Rodham.; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Gorbachev, Mikhail Sergeevich, 1931-.; Goodall, Jane, 1934-.; United States--Social policy.; South Africa.; Child development.; Education--Africa, Sub-Saharan.; International relations--Research.; Education--United States.; Social sciences--Research.; Science--Study and teaching.; Photographs.; Occupation
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least two business days in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Boxes 612-615 contain patient records and are restricted until 2060.
Acquisition
David A. Hamburg and Carnegie Corp. 9/29/2005 2005.2006.M059
Gift of David A. Hamburg and Carnegie Corporation of New York, 2005
Selected Related Material at Columbia
Carnegie Corporation of New York Records
- Series I: Carnegie Corporation of New York
  This series contains the materials relating to dr. Hamburg’s activities as a President of the Carnegie Corporation of New York, the title he assumed in 1982. His corporation files frequently contain earlier background material on various subjects, or fragments of his own earlier writings, which he edited and used as building blocks for subsequent projects. The files reflect five formal program areas, established by Carnegie Corporation: Avoiding Nuclear War (ANW); Education: Science, Technology and the Economy; Prevention of Damage to Children; Strengthening Human Resources in Developing Countries (HRDC); and Special Projects The materials in this series are closely related to the Carnegie Corporation of New York Records collection, held in the RBML.. For official records, such as Board of Trustees documents and grant information, please see the Carnegie Corporation of New York Records. In cases, when holdings, such as agenda books, or printed materials, duplicated between the two collections, the items, already held in the Carnegie Corporation of New York Records were weeded from the Hamburg papers.
  - Subseries I.1: Carnegie Corporation of New York Board Materials
    The series contains chronologically arranged files related to the Board of Trustees meetings of the Carnegie Corporation of New York, including minutes, materials of Agenda Committee, Finance and Administration Committee, Executive Committee, Nomination Committee, and others), meeting preparation materials, background reading, and related correspondence, including some correspondence from the Corporation’s trustees. Box 15 contains notes and background materials for Hamburg's Presidential report to the Board. For official Board of Trustees documents please see the Carnegie Corporation of New York Records collection, Series I.A.3. The materials in Subseries I.1, duplicating the ones, already held in Carnegie Corporation Records Series I.A.3, have been discarded.
    - Board Meetings, April 1983-October 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1-45)
    - Board Meetings, October 1985-June 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1-35)
    - Board Meetings, July 1986-October 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1-49)
    - Board Meetings, November 1987-January 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-56)
    - Board Meetings, April 1989-January 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1-42)
    - Board Meetings, March 1990-January 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1-41)
    - Board Meetings, April 1991-October 1991 (Box 7, Folder 1-40)
    - Board Meetings, September 1991-October 1992 (Box 8, Folder 1-40)
    - Board Meetings, October 1992-October 1993 (Box 9, Folder 1-49)
    - Board Meetings, Presidential Search Committee materials, January 1994-1997 (Box 10, Folder 1-31)
    - Board Meetings, January 1995-October 1995 (Box 11, Folder 1-41)
    - Board Meetings, October 1995-June 1996 (Box 12, Folder 1-35)
    - Board Meetings, DAH retirement project, January 1996-December 1996 (Box 13, Folder 1-24)
    - Board Meetings, Vartan Gregorian's appointment, December 1996-October 1997 (Box 14, Folder 1-21)
    - Board Meetings, President's Report Copies, April 1983-April 1997 (Box 15, Folder 1-54)
  - Subseries I.2: Carnegie Corporation of New York Trustees
    The series contains lists of Carnegie Corporation of New York trustees, handbook and compensation information; mixed correspondence files, and individual files on trustees, arranged alphabetically by name. Additional information about these individuals can frequently be found in Individual Correspondence files in Series III.2. of this colelction and in Carnegie Corporation of New York Records collection, Series I.E.5 (Trustee Files).
    - Trustees List, 1999- (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Trustee Handbook, 1987- (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Trustee Compensation, 1990- (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Trustee Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - CC Trustees, Correspondence and Materials, 2000- (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Trustee Contribution Fund, 1993- (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Beatie, Richard I., 1989-1992 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Celeste, Richard, March 1997- (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Comer, James P., 1988-1996 (Box 16, Folder 9-10)
    - Cota-Robles, Eugene H., 1988-1996 (Box 16, Folder 11-14)
    - Fuller, Ellen V., May 1990- (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Heinz, Teresa, 1985-1997 (Box 16, Folder 16-20)
    - Johnson, James, 1991-1999 (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
    - Kaplan, Helene, 1983-1998 (Box 17, Folder 7-14)
    - Kean, Thomas H., 1988-1997 (Box 17, Folder 15-18)
    - Mai, Vincent, 1990-1997 (Box 17, Folder 19-20)
    - McPherson, Mary Patterson, 1983-1996 (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Malcolm, Shirley, 1983-1996 (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Minow, Newton, 1995-1996 (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Minow, Newton, 1982-1997 (Box 18, Folder 1-16)
    - Minow, Newton, 1993-1997 (Box 19, Folder 1-17)
    - Muller, Henry, 1992-1994 (Box 19, Folder 18-19)
    - Renier, James, 1995-1996 (Box 19, Folder 20-21)
    - Rice, Condoleeza, 1993-1997 (Box 19, Folder 22)
    - Tienda, Marta, 1987-1997 (Box 19, Folder 23)
    - Tisch, Billie, 1996-1997 (Box 19, Folder 24)
    - Tisch, Laurence A., 1985-1994 (Box 19, Folder 25)
    - Watkins, Admiral James D., 1988-1997 (Box 19, Folder 26-28)
    - Woodruff, Judy, 1995-1996 (Box 19, Folder 29)
  - Subseries I.3: Strengthening Human Resources in Developing Countries
    Files relating to Strengthening Human Resources in Developing Countries (HRDC) program area, pursued by the Carnegie Corporation in 1983-1999, which was focused on leadership training for women and underprivilleged groups, supported pioneering research on prevention of maternal mortality, and contibuted to a more robust educational system by, for example, sponsoring the installation of first CD-Rom technologies at University libraries in Tanzania and Zimbabwe. The files include materials on Africa and, to a lesser extent, on other regions, and feature documents from organizations such as Council on Foreign Relations, World Health Organization, etc. Starting in 1986 the HRDC was chaired by the first staff member from Africa, Dr. Adetokunbo Lucas (Nigeria). Related materials can be found in the subseries I.4 (South Africa), as well as in documents from Carnegie Commission for Science, Technology and Development (CCSTG) materials, and Carnegie Commission for Preventing Deadly Conflict (CCPDC).
    - HRDC Materials, Program Papers and Memos 1983-1991, 1982-1984 (Box 20, Folder 1-25)
    - HRDC Materials, ODC/CFR materials, 1984-June 1985 (Box 21, Folder 1-40)
    - Subject files, August 1985-June 1988 (Box 22, Folder 1-42)
    - Subject files, June 1988-March 1990 (Box 23, Folder 1-42)
    - Subject files, March 1990-1995 (Box 24, Folder 1-38)
    - Subject files, 1997- (Box 25, Folder 1-11)
    - Background materials for HRDC, 1982-1997 (Box 25, Folder 12-55)
    - Background materials for HRDC, 1982-1997 (Box 26, Folder 1-52)
  - Subseries I.4: South Africa
    Materials, relating to South Africa, during its period of transition away from the apartaid regime, generated in the course of such Carnegie Corporation projects as HRDC (See subseries I.3) and the Second Carnegie Inquiry into Poverty and Development in Southern Africa. The latter study, based at the University of Cape Town and conducted with participation from the network of scholars and professionals, community leaders, social workers and 20 universities, provided a rare opportunity for research, training, and leadership development for black Africans, and its findings and practical recommendations were widely disseminated. The follow-up to the study included “South Africa: The Cordoned Heart” photo exhibition, and Omar Badsha establishing Centre for Documentary Photography at the University of Cape Town Corporation’s grants made under HRDC rubric, led to Women’s Charter inclusion in new 1994 South African Constitution in 1994—Carnegie grantees Frene Ginwala became first female Speaker of the National Assembly of South African Parliament and Mamphela Ramphele, first black female Vice Chancellor in South Africa at University of Cape Town.
    - Subject files, 1983-1989 (Box 27, Folder 1-33)
    - Subject files, 1985-October 1987 (Box 28, Folder 1-21)
    - Subject files, October 1985-March 1987 (Box 29, Folder 1-18)
    - Subject files, April 1986-April 1988 (Box 30, Folder 1-34)
    - Subject files, June 1988-1989 (Box 31, Folder 1-28)
    - Subject files, 1990-1996 (Box 32, Folder 1-12)
    - Background Materials, 1983-1996 (Box 32, Folder 13-35)
  - Subseries I.5: Carnegie Commission on Science, Technology and Government (CCSTG)